<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>fifo on Lice!</title><link>https://blog.licenser.net/tags/fifo/</link><description>Recent content in fifo on Lice!</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.licenser.net/tags/fifo/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Postmortem of a interesting bug</title><link>https://blog.licenser.net/2014/11/postmortem-of-a-interesting-bug/</link><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.licenser.net/2014/11/postmortem-of-a-interesting-bug/</guid><description>Symptoms After a full network outage in a larger system (7 FiFo instances and, a few dozen of hypervisors, VM's in the 3 digit number) a small percentage of the VM's stored in FiFo lost information which package was assigned to them and which organization they belong to.
Technical background As part of planned maintenance on the switching layer the entire network was taken down. Effectively cutting the communication between any two systems in the network.</description></item><item><title>Post-mortem of a failed support case.</title><link>https://blog.licenser.net/2014/02/post-mortem-of-a-failed-support-case./</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.licenser.net/2014/02/post-mortem-of-a-failed-support-case./</guid><description>Every now and then I check the link reports for Project FiFo to see what people think and write about it. Recently I stumbled about an article that oddly enough made me both proud and sad. It actually was a rather negative one, which is a shame, but on the other hand a project isn't mature until people care enough to complain.
Yet even so it would be very easy to cast this aside as a &amp;lsquo;success&amp;rsquo; in a strange manner, it still bothers me that someone is upset enough with FiFo to spend his time writing a longish blog article and write their own management software.</description></item><item><title>Backups with Project FiFo</title><link>https://blog.licenser.net/2014/01/backups-with-project-fifo/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.licenser.net/2014/01/backups-with-project-fifo/</guid><description>With 0.4.3 FiFo introduces support for LeoFS and this allows for some quite nice new features. Most importantly it decouples FiFo's operations from storing big amounts of data which makes maintaining either of this much more sensible and scaling storage much more easy.
Then again while nice that is not the important part, just storing datasets somewhere else does not make much of a difference for most users but what LoeFS allows FiFo to store much more data then would be good in the old setup.</description></item></channel></rss>